A Guide to the Bishop William H. Marmion Papers 1932-1981
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
- Bishop of Southwestern Virginia 1954-1979
  - Administrative Files
    - General Convention--Agenda Committee (Box-folder 21-5)
    - Gneral Convention Conference--Pre-Conference (Box-folder 21-6)
    - Gifts and Bequests (Box-folder 21-7)
    - Bryan Green Preaching Mission (Box-folder 21-8)
    - Bishop William J. Gordon (Box-folder 22-1)
    - H.C. for Children (Box-folder 22-2)
    - Help-Inc--Bethany Hall, Half-way House for Women (Box-folder 22-3)
    - Captain Robert Hicks (Box-folder 22-3)
    - Historical Society of Episcopal Church (Box-folder 22-5)
    - Histographer--Council (Box-folder 22-6)
    - Histographer--Dr. Marshall Fishwick (Box-folder 22-7,8)
    - Hollins (Box-folder 22-9)
    - Hood Conference--Province of Washington (Box-folder 22-10)
    - House of Bishops (Box-folder 22-11,12,13)
    - House of Bishops (Box-folder 23-1,2,3,4)
    - House of Bishops--New Orleans, Louisiana (Box-folder 23-5)
    - House of Bishops Meeting--Pocono Manov, Pennsylvania (Box-folder 23-6)
    - Housing--Low Income (Box-folder 23-7)
    - Indian Work--National Committee (Box-folder 23-8)
    - Indian Work (Box-folder 23-9)
    - Institutional Chaplaincy (Box-folder 24-1,2)
    - Institutional Chaplaincy--Advisory Board (Box-folder 24-4)
    - Institutional Chaplaincy--Staunton Area (Box-folder 24-5)
    - Institutional Chaplaincy (Box-folder 24-6)
    - Institution for Advanced Pastoral Studies, INC (Box-folder 24-7)
    - Insurance Plan for the Diocese (Box-folder 24-8)
    - Jesus in the Church Today (Box-folder 24-9)
    - Joint Committee on Christian Citizenship (Box-folder 25-1)
    - Joint Urban Advisory Committee (Box-folder 25-2)
    - Jones, Martha DeBrey (Box-folder 25-3)
    - Lay Administration of the Chalice (Box-folder 25-4)
    - Lay Ministries Division (Box-folder 25-5)
    - Lay Reader's Information (Box-folder 25-6)
    - Lay Readers-Training (Box-folder 25-7)
    - Levels of Authority in the Church (Box-folder 25-8)
    - Life in the Spirit Commission (Box-folder 25-9)
    - Liturgical Commission of the Diocese (Box-folder 25-10,11,12)
    - Liturgical Commission of the Episcopal Church (Box-folder 25-13)
    - Liturgical Commission of the Diocese (Box-folder 26-1)
    - New Liturgy, The (Box-folder 26-2)
    - Long Range Planning Commission (Box-folder 26-3)
    - Long Range Planning and Strategy for Mission (Box-folder 26-4)
    - Marin Fund (Box-folder 26-5)
    - Marriage--Advisory Committee to the Bishop (Box-folder 26-6)
    - Marriage--Canon 18 Study (Box-folder 26-7)
    - Marriage Services (Box-folder 26-8)
    - Marriages (Box-folder 26-9)
    - Massey, Denton (Box-folder 26-10)
    - Maxwell, John (Box-folder 26-11)
    - Map of the Diocese (Box-folder 26-12)
    - Men of the Diocese (Box-folder 26-13)
    - Mid-Atlantic Career Center (Box-folder 26-14)
    - Mid-Atlantic Parish Training Program (Box-folder 27-1)
    - Mid-Winters (Box-folder 27-2)
    - Mingea Fund (Box-folder 27-3)
    - Ministry--Commission (Box-folder 27-4)
    - Lay Ministries (Box-folder 27-5)
    - Ministry Commission (Box-folder 27-6)
    - Ministry--Resort Areas (Box-folder 27-7)
    - Ministry--New Forms (Box-folder 27-8)
    - Miscellaneous--General Convention (Box-folder 27-9)
    - Missions (Box-folder 27-10)
    - Missions Department (Box-folder 28-1)
    - Missions--Diocese (Box-folder 28-2,3)
    - Missions--Outreach (Box-folder 28-4)
    - Missions--Statistical Information (Box-folder 28-5)
    - Missions--Task Force on Local Missions (Box-folder 28-6)
    - Mutual Responsiblity Presentation at Lexinton (Box-folder 28-7)
    - Mutual Responsiblity and Interdependence (Box-folder 28-8)
    - Correspondence Regarding Mutual Responsiblity and Interdependence in the Body of Christ--M.R.I. (Box-folder 28-9)
    - Reports Regarding mutual Responsiblity and Interdependence in the Body of christ (Box-folder 28-10)
    - (Box-folder 28-11)
    - Mutual Responsiblity and Interdependence--MRI Division (Box-folder 29-1)
    - Mutual Responsiblity and Interdependence--Course for Laymen (Box-folder 29-2)
    - Mutual Responsibility and Interdependence--Receiving (Box-folder 29-3)
    - National Association of Episcopal Schools (Box-folder 29-4)
    - National Committee on Tithing and Investment (Box-folder 29-5)
    - National Council on the Churches of Christ in the United States of America (Box-folder 29-6)
    - National Council of Churches--Capsule Report (Box-folder 29-7)
    - Newman, Samuel M.D. (Box-folder 29-8)
    - Non-Stipendary Ministry (Box-folder 29-9)
    - Northeast Career Center, The (Box-folder 29-10)
    - Organ Donor Program (Box-folder 29-11)
    - Parish Administration (Box-folder 29-12)
    - Pastoral Development (Box-folder 30-2,3)
    - Pathway Schools, INC (Box-folder 30-4)
    - Pension Plan--Lay Employees (Box-folder 30-5)
    - Pheobe Needles (Box-folder 30-6)
    - Peobe Needles Memorial Conference Center (Box-folder 30-7)
    - Planning Division (Box-folder 30-8)
    - Prayer Commission (Box-folder 30-11)
    - Preaching Mission Remarks (Box-folder 30-12)
    - Presiding Bishop Allen (Box-folder 30-13)
    - Promotion Department--Diocese (Box-folder 31-1)
    - Projects for Partnership (Box-folder 31-2)
    - Provincial Council (Box-folder 31-3)
    - Province III Synod (Box-folder 31-4,5,6)
    - Province III--Nominating Committe (Box-folder 31-7)
    - Province III--Bishops (Box-folder 31-8)
    - Province III (Box-folder 31-9)
    - Provincial Synod, St. Paul's Church, Richmond, VA (Box-folder 31-10)
    - Province of Washington (Box-folder 31-11)
    - Radford Colege (Box-folder 32-1,2,3,4,5,6)
    - Roanoke Area--Denominational Executives (Box-folder 32-7)
    - Resource Development (Box-folder 32-8)
    - Registrar (Box-folder 32-9)
    - Religious Situation, The (Box-folder 32-10)
    - Reorganization of Evans House Staff (Box-folder 32-11)
    - Research and Field Study (Box-folder 32-12)
    - Resolutions (Box-folder 32-13)
    - Restricted Pledges (Box-folder 32-14)
    - Retarded Children's Home (Box-folder 32-15)
    - Revolving Loans--Guidelines (Box-folder 32-16)
    - Right to Work Laws (Box-folder 32-17)
    - Thomas A. Scott Memorial (Box-folder 32-18)
    - Schismatic Movement (Box-folder 32-19)
    - Sexuality--Task Force (Box-folder 32-20)
    - Social Service (Box-folder 32-21)
    - Special Funds Grants (Box-folder 32-22)
    - Standing Committee (Box-folder 33-1,2)
    - Stewardship and Promotion (Box-folder 33-3,4)
    - southwestern Episcopal Homes (Box-folder 33-5)
    - Committee on the State of the Church (Box-folder 33-6)
    - Stuart Hall Board of Trustees (Box-folder 33-7)
    - Stuart Hall Anniversary (Box-folder 33-8)
    - (Box-folder 33-9)
    - Teaching and Education (Box-folder 33-10)
    - Total Action Against Poverty (Box-folder 33-11)
    - Town and Country Work (Box-folder 33-12)
    - United Thank Offering (Box-folder 34-1,2)
    - Virginia Education Fund (Box-folder 34-4)
    - Vacancy Consultation--Diocese (Box-folder 34-5)
    - Venture in Mission (Box-folder 34-6,7)
    - Venture in Mission--Reports (Box-folder 34-8)
    - Virginia Coalition on Nutrition--Veterans' Administration (Box-folder 35-1)
    - Viginina Committee for Public Schools (Box-folder 35-2)
    - Virginia Episcopal School (Box-folder 35-3)
    - Voluntary Plan of Christian Stewardship (Box-folder 35-4)
    - Warden's Conference (Box-folder 35-5)
    - Women Workers (Box-folder 35-6)
    - Women of the Diocese (Box-folder 35-7)
    - Worship of the Church (Box-folder 35-8,9)
    - Year of Achievement (Box-folder 35-10)
    - Youth Conference Materials (Box-folder 35-11)
  - Civil Rights
    Contents of the second sub-series, Civil Rights, include brochures, correspondence, magazine articles, and newspaper articles which Marmion either collected or produced on the civil rights movement, mainly from the 1950's and 1960's. Included in this series are documents relating to the controversy over the biracial conferences at Hemlock Haven, a retreat near Marion, Virginia purchased by the diocese in 1957. While Marmion maintained the view that the youth conferences should be open to members of both races, many lay members of the diocese opposed mixed race conferences for young people, and only after five years of debate did the facility open to camps attended jointly by whites and African-Americans. The Bishop's yearly files on race relations from 1954-1965 also offer firsthand insight on the civil rights movement in the United States
    - Advisory Committee on Intergroup Relations (Box-folder 36-1)
    - Birmingham Bombing (Box-folder 36-2)
    - Black Manifesto (Box-folder 36-3,4)
    - Church and Race (Box-folder 36-5,6)
    - Civil Disorders (Box-folder 36-7)
    - Civil Rights (Box-folder 36-8)
    - Civil Rights Act (Box-folder 36-9)
    - Civil Rights Bill (Box-folder 36-10)
    - Civil Rights Bill (Box-folder 37-1)
    - Commission on Interracial Problems and Dating (Box-folder 37-2)
    - Committee on Church and Race (Box-folder 37-3)
    - Council (Box-folder 37-4,5)
    - Daniels, Jonathan (Box-folder 37-6)
    - Department of Christian Education (Box-folder 37-7)
    - Freedom Riders (Box-folder 37-8)
    - General Convention II (Box-folder 37-9)
    - General Convention II (Box-folder 38-1,2,3,4,5)
    - General Convention II--Bishop Marmion's Letter (Box-folder 38-6)
    - "Letter from Birmingham County Jail"--by Dr. Martin Luther King (Box-folder 38-7)
    - Gray Plan (Box-folder 38-8)
    - Hemlock Haven--Board of Governors (Box-folder 39-1)
    - Hemlock Haven (Box-folder 39-2)
    - Hemlock Haven--Board of Managers (Box-folder 39-3)
    - Hemlock Haven--Clergy Conference Dedication (Box-folder 39-4)
    - Hemlock Haven--Committee of Twenty- Four (Box-folder 39-5)
    - Hemlock Haven Contributors--Operating Budget for 1961 (Box-folder 39-6)
    - Hemlock Haven Director (Box-folder 39-7)
    - Hemlock Haven Enrollment Policy (Box-folder 39-8,9,10,11)
    - Hemlock Haven--General (Box-folder 40-1,2)
    - Hemlock Haven--Labor Day Weekend (Box-folder 40-3)
    - Hemlock Haven--Clergy Conference on Matters of Race--North Carolina Diocese (Box-folder 40-4)
    - Hemlock Haven--Policy, By Laws, Charter (Box-folder 40-5)
    - Hemlock Haven--Policies (Box-folder 40-6)
    - Hemlock Haven--Promotion (Box-folder 40-7)
    - Hemlock Haven--Special Study Committee (Box-folder 40-8)
    - Hemlock Haven Standing Committee--Diocese of Southwestern Virginia (Box-folder 40-9)
    - Hemlock Haven--Statement of Cary White (Box-folder 40-10)
    - Hemlock Haven--Task Force (Box-folder 40-11,12)
    - Hemlock Haven--Tennis Weekend (Box-folder 41-1)
    - Hemlock Haven--Youth Conference (Box-folder 41-2)
    - Lit-in Demonstrators (Box-folder 41-3)
    - March on Washington, The (Box-folder 41-4)
    - National Conference on Religion and Race (Box-folder 41-5,6)
    - National Church, 281 4th Avenue, New York, New York--General (Box-folder 41-7)
    - Pastoral Letter 1956--Answers (Box-folder 41-8)
    - Project Equality (Box-folder 42-1)
    - Race (Box-folder 42-2)
    - Race Relations (Box-folder 42-3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13)
    - Race Realtions--General (Box-folder 42-14)
    - Race Relations--General (Box-folder 43-1)
    - Race Relations Committee (Box-folder 43-2)
    - Race Relations Planning Conference (Box-folder 43-3)
    - Race Relations--The Southwestern Episcopalian (Box-folder 43-4)
    - Race Relations--Washington, D.C. (Box-folder 43-5)
    - Roanoke Conference on Interracial Cooperation (Box-folder 43-6)
    - Selma, Alabama Crisis (Box-folder 43-7)
    - The Southern Episcopalian Pastoral Letter, from Bishop Marmion on School Issues (Box-folder 43-8)
    - Southern Frontier (Box-folder 43-9)
    - Stouffer Foundation (Box-folder 43-10)
    - Teeter, John H. (Box-folder 43-11)
    - West, Francis (Box-folder 43-12)
  - International Affairs
    The third sub-series, International Affairs, includes correspondence and related documents detailing the Bishop's activities in overseas affairs. A large number of the folders detail companion diocese relationships with churches in Great Britain and Ecuador, and under the umbrella of this liaison Marmion made visits to both countries. Also included in this sub-series are documents that outline Marmion's opposition to apartheid in South Africa. Believing economic sanctions were key to forcing the South African government to end the racial discrimination of the apartheid system, in 1969 the Bishop chaired a committee to prevent the Episcopal Church from using banks which supported that country's government. Marmion's argument was persuasive, and the church agreed not to utilize banking firms who financed South Africa.
    - Bayne, Stephen F. (Bishop) (Box-folder 44-1)
    - Bradford--Companion Diocese (Box-folder 44-2)
    - Bradford Clergy Conference (Box-folder 44-3)
    - Bradford--Companion Diocese (Box-folder 44-4)
    - Bradford Tour (Box-folder 44-6,7,8)
    - Church School Missionary Offering (Box-folder 44-9)
    - Drummy, Richard (Box-folder 44-10)
    - Ecuador (Box-folder 44-11,12)
    - Ecuador (Box-folder 45-1)
    - Ecuador Accident (Box-folder 45-2)
    - Ecuador--Bishop Caceres (Box-folder 45-3)
    - Ecuador--Bishop Request (Box-folder 45-4)
    - Ecuador (Box-folder 45-5)
    - Ecuador Committee (Box-folder 45-6)
    - Ecuador (Box-folder 45-7)
    - Ecuador--Layman's Tour (Box-folder 45-8)
    - Ecuador--Lift Up Thine eyes (Box-folder 45-9)
    - Ecuador--Youth Exchange (Box-folder 45-10)
    - Guatemala--Expulsion of Bishop Frey (Box-folder 45-11)
    - Lambeth (Box-folder 45-12,13,14)
    - Lambeth Conference (Box-folder 46-1,2)
    - Lambeth 1978--Reports and Resolutions (Box-folder 46-3)
    - Middle East (Box-folder 46-4)
    - Missionaries (Box-folder 46-5)
    - Ovamboland (Box-folder 46-6)
    - Rhodesia (Box-folder 46-7)
    - Social Responsbility in Investments (Box-folder 46-8)
    - South Africa--Episcopal Churchmen (Box-folder 46-9)
    - South Africa (Box-folder 46-10,11,12)
    - South Africe (Box-folder 47-1)
    - White House Conference on International Cooperation (Box-folder 47-2)
    - World Council of Churches (Box-folder 47-3)
    - World Hunger--Diocesan Committee (Box-folder 47-4)
    - World Relief and Interchurch Aid (Box-folder 47-5,6)
  - Vietnam War
    The fourth and smallest sub-series, Vietnam War, includes brochures, correspondence, magazine articles, and newspaper clippings on the war in Vietnam between 1964 and 1975. The Bishop advocated ending the conflict in Southeast Asia, and his participation in a public anti-war demonstration in Roanoke drew the ire of some of his parishioners. Called both communist and un-patriotic, Marmion nevertheless sought to influence the United States government to seek an end to military involvement in Vietnam
    - Clemency/Earned Re-entry (Box-folder 48-1)
    - Draft Counseling Services (Box-folder 48-2)
    - Episcopal Peace Fellowship (Box-folder 48-3)
    - International Peace Advisory Committee (Box-folder 48-4)
    - Prisoners of War (Box-folder 48-5)
    - Vietnam (Box-folder 48-6)
    - Vietnam War and the United States (Box-folder 48-7)